Hey בוקר טוב, boker tov, חג שמח. chag sameach. Good יום העצמאות,
Yom Ha'atzmaut, 19th day of the עומר, Omer, and we are in
דף סב, Daf Samech-Bet, 62. We pick up at the middle of
סא עמוד ב. Samech-Aleph amud bet. We went through the whole debate
of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי חנינא בן גמליאל Rabbi Chanina
ben Gamliel about whether you can learn from בני גד ובני ראובן
Bnei Gad u'Bnei Reuven the requirement of doubling a תנאי, tnai, and
without saying the negative part of the תנאי, tnai, should we assume
the action is binding even if the condition is not met? It
is interesting, I just cannot resist because it is יום העצמאות, Yom
Ha'atzmaut, mentioning the comment that, you know, the discussion yesterday was about
participating with the people and going into the land and getting a
portion of the land, and then the people that sort of stayed
outside of the land and took their portion outside of the land.
That's interesting reflecting about that as somebody living in חוץ לארץ chutz
la'aretz on יום העצמאות. Yom Ha'atzmaut. We sort of chosen our own
little עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden here so we can have that discussion
some other time. But anyway, but okay, find other ways to support
from a distance. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara picks up in the following,
the middle of סא עמוד ב. Samech-Aleph amud bet.
Okay, the גמרא Gemara says like this: בשלמא לרבי מאיר היינו דכתיב.
Bishlama le-Rabbi Meir haynu de-chtiv. It's right near where it begins according
to the פסוק pasuk where it says בראשית ד, Bereishit Daled, I'm
almost exactly in the middle in the left-hand margin between the גמרא
Gemara and רש"י. Rashi. בשלמא לרבי מאיר היינו דכתיב. Bishlama le-Rabbi Meir
haynu de-chtiv. So now we're going to look at various פסוקים psukim
in the תורה Torah and see whether the פסוקים psukim feel the
need to speak about when it says if X then Y, then
it needs to say if not X then not
Y. So בשלמא לרבי מאיר היינו דכתיב, Bishlama le-Rabbi Meir haynu de-chtiv,
אם תטיב שאת, Im Tetiv Seat, that you know, God says to
קין, Kayin, if you do good, it will be forgiven. ואם לא
תטיב, Ve-im lo tetiv, and if you do not do good, לפתח
חטאת רובץ, la-petach chatat rovetz, that sin crouches by the door by
the door. So, so you have to say, if it's good this
and if you don't do good, it'll be the opposite, okay, because
it wouldn't be implied. So you see you don't say מכלל לאו
אתה שומע הן. miklal lav ata shomea hen. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אלא לרבי חנינא בן גמליאל למה לי, Ella le-Rabbi Chanina ben
Gamliel lama li, why for רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina did you have
to say the flip side? No, סלקא דעתך אמינא salqa da’takh amina
no, because I needed to say it, because I would have thought
אם תטיב אגרא, im tetiv agra, you'll be rewarded. אם לא תטיב,
Im lo tetiv, but if you don't do good, לא אגרא ולא
דינא, lo agra ve-lo dina, you won't be rewarded but you won't
be punished. So, right, so it's without saying the תנאי tnai without
repeating it, sort of like the discussions we had. If you didn't
say what happens if you don't go over into the land, would
that, you know, what would I have assumed? So without repeating, without
doing the flip side, I would have known you wouldn't have been
rewarded, but I wouldn't have known anything more than that, I wouldn't
have known you would have been punished. So therefore קא משמע לן,
kamashmalan, that's why it has to say the flip side. Now I
should stop pause right here and just say that this is not,
you know, is the גמרא Gemara assuming that these are applications of
a legal principle that if you don't say a double condition then
the act is going to be binding regardless? Are we supposed to
read the פסוקים psukim in the תורה Torah that we're looking at
as though God is making a תנאי, tnai, this, you know, promise
will take effect in condition X and you know, and then legally
what will happen if you know, it's like a legal halachic question
about the need for double condition? Or is it, it's hard to
read that obviously in the פסוקים, psukim, right, we're not dealing about
some like a legal act or whatever. But what it seems like
we're dealing with is a language question, right, which is just a
simple point when people say if X then Y, are we entitled
to infer the reverse? And we discussed how from a technical, you
know, prepositional logic perspective we're not entitled to infer the reverse even
though by a common language logic we are. So that's why you
can look at sort of פסוקים, psukim, you don't have to see
them through this halachic lens. And that's more framed by, you know,
there's two ways of articulating רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position. One is
כל תנאי שאינו כתנאי בני גד ובני ראובן kol tnai she-eino ke-tnai
Bnei Gad u-Bnei Reuven is not a תנאי, tnai, which is a
very technical halachic legal
position about certain acts that are stipulated and whether the stipulation prevents
the effect of the act. There's another way that רבי מאיר's Rabbi
Meir position is articulated which is מכלל לאו אי אתה שומע הן
ומכלל הן אי אתה שומע לאו, miklal lav ee ata shomea hen
ve-miklal hen ee ata shomea lav, which has nothing to do with
which is not itself formulated as a halachic point, it's a linguistic
point. From when somebody says yes, the positive you can't infer the
negative, and if somebody says the negative you can't infer the positive,
okay, which is a simple point about how do we parse language
and how rigorous are we in the you know, in applying a
certain logic, you know, formal logic to language. And that seems to
be more what the גמרא Gemara is doing here, although throughout this
סוגיא sugya תוספות Tosafos tries to fit this in to the more
classic halachic issue of a תנאי tnai and read it through that
lens. Okay, so let's see the next case. Okay, קא
משמע לן. kamashmalan. בשלמא לרבי מאיר היינו דכתיב, Bishlama le-Rabbi Meir haynu
de-chtiv, it works for רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that's what's meant by
the verse, אז תנקה מאלתי, az tinakeh me-alati, right, when אברהם Avraham
speaks to his servant and says, you know, and if you go
to that land and they don't give you, you know, he makes
him take a שבועה shvua that you will not take a wife
from בנות כנען bnot Canaan for my son, and if you go
to that land and they don't give the girl to you, then
you'll be cleansed.
The עבד eved says, what?
אז תנקה מאלתי?
az tinakeh me-alati?
No,
אברהם Avraham is saying it, okay. What will happen if they... אז
תנקה מאלתי az tinakeh me'alati is אברהם Avraham talking. It's my oath.
Okay. So if you do not go, if you go to that
land and they don't give it to you, then you'll be cleansed.
Okay, so you have to sort of say, you know, you're under
the ban if not, you know, the שבועה, shvua, but if you
don't, then you'll be clean from it. If you, you know, so
אל רבי חנינא בן גמליאל למה לי, El Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel
lama li, why do you need to sort of say the flip?
Now, it's a funny question as תוספות Tosafot already asks, because the
oath was you cannot take a girl from בנות כנען, bnot Canaan,
right? So, you know, so what are we supposed to assume? That
if he...
Wait, wait, listen. It's the עבד eved recounting it to לבן.
Lavan. Oh, it's the repetition of it. Oh, thank you. Okay, fine.
It was not... thank you, I misunderstood you. But when אברהם... Avraham...
thank you. So that's a good point, it's when the עבד eved
repeats it, you know, there. But when אברהם Avraham initially says it,
let's look at when אברהם Avraham initially says it. Thank you, Michael.
Okay, so it says: ואשביעך בה׳ אלהי השמים ואלהי הארץ אשר לא
תקח אשה
לבני מבנות הכנעני. v'ashbiacha b'Hashem elokei hashamayim v'elokei ha'aretz asher lo
tikach isha livni mibnot hakanaani.
You cannot take a daughter from... a wife from בנות הכנעני. bnot
hakanaani. כי אל ארצי, ki el artzi, you have to go to
my land. ואולי לא תאבה האשה ללכת אחרי. v'ulay lo taveh ha'isha
lalechet acharai. You... so no... nevertheless, you cannot take a girl from
this land... הוא ישלח מלאכו לפניך ולקחת אשה לבני משם ואם לא
תאבה האשה ללכת אחריך ונקית משבעתי זאת רק את בני לא תשב
שמה. hu yishlach malacho lefanecha v'lakachta isha livni misham v'im lo taveh
ha'isha lalechet acharecha v'nikita mishvuati zot rak et bni lo tashev shama.
You'll be cleansed from my שבועה shvua but just don't return my
son there. Now, first of all, there's an interesting question, what does
it mean you'll be cleansed from my שבועה? shvua? Does that mean
that you'll be able to take a daughter from בנות כנען? bnot
Canaan? That's what רש״י Rashi says. רש״י Rashi says: וקח לו אשה
מבנות ענר אשכול וממרא. v'kach lo isha mibnot Aner Eshkol u'Mamre.
Okay. Yeah, you will be cleansed and you'll be free to take
a daughter from בנות כנעני bnot Kanaani if you go ahead and
you do... and you do that. Okay, but let's take a look
at תוספות. Tosafot. Okay, so תימא tema says, says: מה ענין זה
אצל מחלוקת בית שמאי ורבי מאיר, ma inyan zeh etzel machloket Beit
Shammai v'Rabbi Meir, says תוספות. Tosafot. והלא לא היה תנאי אלא בפירוש
אמר לו שישבע לו שיקח אשה לבנו ממשפחתו. v'halo lo haya tnai
ela b'peresh amar lo sheyishava lo sheyikach isha livno mimishpachto. He didn't
say, if X then Y. He said, take an oath that you
won't do it. Okay, he didn't say, take an oath that, you
know, that if you do X then you will be punished or
something like that, I don't know. ואם לא פירש הקרא ונקית משבועתי
ואם לא יתנו לך. v'im lo peresh hakra v'nikita mishvuati v'im lo
yitnu lecha. If he did not say, oh, but if you go
ahead and do the following things, then I... then, you know, then
my oath no longer is binding. אם לא יתנו לך הייתי אומר,
im lo yitnu lecha hayiti omer, if they hadn't said that, I
would have said שהיה עובר שבועה בין יתנו בין לא יתנו אם
לא היה מביא אשה. shehaya over shvua bein yitnu bein lo yitnu
im lo haya mevi isha. Right? I would have said that, you
know, he made an oath and... he would have been bound by
the oath regardless, תוספות Tosafot says that he would have been bound
by the oath to bring a wife back, he certainly would have
been bound by the oath not to take a woman from בנות
כנען. bnot Canaan. Okay, so that's his question. The answer is less
satisfying than the question. Okay, but let's anyway continue in the גמרא.
Gemara. The גמרא Gemara sort of says: here was the oath to
do this, can I not according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir have
assumed that if he somehow had attempted to do it and not
succeeded he would have been free from the oath? I mean, could
I not have assumed that? The fact that you have to spell
that out means that you have to always spell out the flip
side. Again, this is evidence that we're not just talking about a
question of תנאי. tnai. We're talking about a question of like what
you can infer from language. So he had to spell out the
flip side. So the גמרא Gemara says: אלא רבי חנינא בן גמליאל
למה לי? Ela Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel lama li? Why did you
need to spell out the flip side? איצטריך, Itzterich, you need it.
סלקא דעתך אמינא היכא דניחא ליה לדידיה ולא ניחא ליה לדידהו מייתי
בעל כרחייהו. Salqa da'atach amina heicha d'nicha leh l'dideh v'lo nicha leh
l'didhu meiti b'al korchayhu. Maybe he's not free from the oath if
she wants to but the parents don't want to, and then he
would have to like bring her against their will if he could
succeed... if he could succeed in doing that. Okay, and if he
didn't then he would actually have transgressed the oath. Maybe you didn't
have an out, the parents' objection maybe אברהם Avraham wouldn't have considered
a legitimate out. קא משמע לן, Ka mashma lan, it says: ואם
לא יתנו לך. v'im lo yitnu lecha. If they don't give to
you. So to make it clear that you're... that it's a legitimate
out that they didn't want it, even if she does want it.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: קא משמע לן ואם לא תאבה
האשה למה לי? Ka mashma lan v'im lo taveh ha'isha lama li?
So why do I need the other part? Not if they don't
want, but if she doesn't want. So the answer is already now
obvious. איצטריך, Itzterich, I need it. סלקא דעתך אמינא היכא דניחא להו
לדידהו ולא ניחא לה לדידה מייתי בעל כרחה. Salqa da'atach amina heicha
d'nicha lhu l'didhu v'lo nicha la l'didah meiti b'al karchah. Let's say
the parents want and if she doesn't want, bring her against her
objections, which is interesting, which is probably how it was always done,
and that's always why it's fascinating that in that story the, you
know, רבקה Rivka gets an opportunity to voice her... to voice her
objection. Okay, קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan that אברהם Avraham is
saying to him that either way you are free. Okay, so without
saying the flip side I maybe could have inferred that if you
attempted and didn't succeed you'd... you'd not be bound by it, but
I would not have known exactly what would have
constituted not succeeding, and that's why אברהם Avraham had to spell it
out explicitly that either them objecting or her objecting would have been
enough.
Okay, but again this was not a really case of a תנאי
tnai and that again points to the fact that we're not dealing
just with proving a halachic point about תנאים. tnaim. Also even in
this whole process, they're just mixing and matching, "and if you be
cleansed of my oath" is the recounting, ואם לא תאבה האשה v'im
lo taveh ha'isha is when אברהם Avraham actually says. I know, they're...
yeah, they're conflating it all as reporting the same story. Okay. בשיטה
דרבי מאיר היינו דכתיב. Bishita de-Rabbi Meir hayinu de-ketiv. Now he has
a more classic תנאי, tnai, although again whether it's a הלכתי halakhic
תנאי tnai is a different point. Anyway, that the following verses make
sense. אם בחקתי תלכו, Im bechukotai telekhu, if you follow my my
my laws, my edicts, you'll get all this reward. And then it
says, ואם בחקתי תמאסו, V'im bechukotai timasu, but it has to still
say the flip side: and if you despise my edicts, then you'll
get all this punishment. So you had to, just because you said
the positive, you have to make it clear the reverse is in
case of the negative. אלא לרבי חנינא בן גמליאל למה לי? Ela
l'Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel lama li? Why do you have to say
both sides? איצטריך, Itzterich, you need to. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salaka daitach
amina, אם בחקתי תלכו ברכה: Im bechukotai telekhu bracha: if you follow
my מצוות, mitzvos, you'll get a ברכה. bracha. אם בחקתי תמאסו, Im
bechukotai timasu, but if you despise my מצוות, mitzvos, לא ברכה ולא
קללה. Lo bracha v'lo klala. Okay, you won't get a ברכה, bracha,
but nothing bad will happen to you. Meaning that the only point
about, you know, it is the idea about the repetition of it
is only to say you don't get what was promised in the
first clause, right? You don't know that there would be the opposite
would take effect. That needs to be spelled out. So yes, already
implicit is if you don't do the מצוה, mitzvah, you don't get
the ברכה, bracha, but it's not spelling out what you do what
does happen if you if you reject the מצוות mitzvos and despise
the מצוות. mitzvos. Okay, קמשמע לן, kamashma lan, that that's why it
has to spell it out, which makes a lot of sense. Okay,
בשיטה דרבי מאיר היינו דכתיב, Bishita de-Rabbi Meir hayinu de-ketiv, according to
Rabbi Meir it makes sense what's said, אם תאבו ושמרתם, Im tovu
ushmartem, if you desire and listen, you know, טוב הארץ תאכלו, tuv
ha'aretz tokhelu, is that the end of the פסוק? pasuk? Something like
that. Okay, then you'll eat from the good of the land. ואם
תמאנו ומריתם, V'im temanu u-meritem, but if you reject and you and
you and you rebel, then you know you'll be you'll be consumed
by the sword. חרב תאכלו. Cherev tukhallu. אלא, Ela, so you have
to say both sides. אלא לרבי חנינא בן גמליאל למה לי? Ela
l'Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel lama li? Why do you need to say
both sides? You know, if you don't do what was the condition,
you won't get what was promised. So same point. איצטריך, סלקא דעתך
אמינא, Itstrich salka daitach amina, אם תאבו טובה: Im tovu tova: if
you do the right thing, you'll get good you'll get good. ואם
תמאנו, V'im temanu, and if you and if you rebel and reject,
לא טובה ולא רעה. lo tova v'lo ra'a. I would have said,
okay, you don't get what was promised, you don't get the good
thing, I wouldn't have known what I wouldn't have known that you
got the bad thing, I wouldn't have known what, you know, קמשמע
לן kamashma lan that it's spelling out. So that's very clear. All
Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel says is if you say if, you know,
if X then Y means if you don't have to say the
flip side, it's already clear if not X then not Y according
to him. But it doesn't tell you anything other than not getting
what was promised in the first clause, what was said in the
first clause. Okay, now that we've quoted this פסוק, pasuk, we're going
to have a moment of a little exegesis digression. מאי חרב תאכלו?
Mai cherev tukhallu? What does it mean 'the sword will be consuming',
which is a funny way, right? It means probably the sword will
consume you, but the grammar's a little funny. So אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, מילחא גללניתא נהמא דשערי עקושא ובצלי, milcha galulanita nahama d'se'arei akusha
u'vatzli, basically it's like it's like a sort of like coarse salt
with hard barley bread ובצלי u'vatzli with onions. Meaning that's what you're
going to eat. You're going to eat barley bread dipped in salt
with onions. Why? דאמר מר, D'amar mar, פת פחני חריבא במלח ובצלי
קשים לגוף כחרבות, pat pachni chariva b'melach u'vatzli kashim l'guph k'charavot, because
like you know plain whatever hard bread and salt and onions are
as bad to the body as swallowing swords. So that's חרב תאכלו,
cherev tukhallu, you'll eat swords. You'll eat food that will like tear
up your insides. Okay, בשלמא לרבי חנינא בן גמליאל, Bishlama l'Rabbi Chanina
ben Gamliel,
now here's a verse that supports Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel. היינו דכתיב,
Hayinu de-ketiv, אם לא שכב איש אותך ואם לא שטית טומאה תחת
אישך הנקי: Im lo shakhav ish otakh v'im lo satit tuma tachat
ishekh hinaki: if a man didn't sleep with you and if you
did not, you know, stray from your husband, then you will be
cleansed. But it doesn't say and if you and if you did
stray from your husband, you will be punished. Now it does go
on to say
והשביע הכהן את האשה בשבועת האלה ואמר לאשה ואת כי שטית טומאה
תחת אישך וכי נטמאת ויתן איש בך את שכבתו והבא המים. V'hishbia
hakohen et ha'isha b'shvuat ha'ala v'amar l'isha v'at ki satit tuma tachat
ishekh v'chi nitmet v'yiten ish bakh et shkhavto v'hava hamayim. So it
does sound like that's the reverse. But רש''י Rashi says that's a
different שבועה, shvua, it's a different type of a thing. Anyway, the
funny thing about that is that it presumes that she did sin:
כי שטית, ki satit, I guess כי ki could be read 'if',
but the language is funny, language more presumes that she did sin.
Anyway, so that is seen as a separate שבועה shvua and this
שבועה shvua only has the 'if you didn't you won't be punished'
and does not have the flip side. So Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel:
you don't need to say the flip side. אלא לרבי מאיר הנקי
מיבעי ליה? Ela l'Rabbi Meir hinaki mibei lei? It should have said,
'and if you did stray you'll be strangled', it's obviously a play
on words on הנקי, hinaki, 'you'll be cleansed', but there's also leading
into the answer. אמר רבי תנחום, Amar Rabbi Tanchum, הנקי כתיב. hinaki
ketiv. Yes, it's written הנקי hinaki without a י. yud. Apparently רש''י
Rashi says that if it was written מלא malei it would have
had an extra י yud between the ה heh and the נ.
nun. And therefore it's in order to make the דרשה drasha of
חינקי. chinaki. Yes, the flip side is implicit there. If you didn't
stray, you'll be cleansed, הנקי, hinaki, and implicit, if you did stray,
or another way to read the פסוק, pasuk, you know, is 'and
if you did stray חינקי, chinaki, you'll be strangled'. Okay, so the
flip side is hidden in the פסוק, pasuk, it is in
the פסוק. pasuk. בשלמא לרבי מאיר היינו דכתיב הנקי. Bishlama l'Rabbi Meir
hayinu de-ketiv hinaki. That's why it uses the word הנקי hinaki to
suggest the חינקי chinaki דרשה. drasha. Right, now that's a support for
him. אלא רבי חנינא בן גמליאל למה לי? Ela Rabbi Chanina ben
Gamliel lama li? Why does it say it in that phrase that
suggests the flip side? So, איצטריך Itzterich, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salaka daitach
amina,
I would have thought, same part as we said before, אם לא
שכב איש, im lo shachav ish, if you did not commit adultery,
הנקי, hinaki, you'll be cleansed. אם שכב, im shachav, but if you
did sleep with another man, לא הנקי, lo hinaki, you won't be
cleansed, ולא חנקי, velo chinaki, and you won't be strangled. אלא איסורא
בעלמא, ela issura be'alma, you'll transgress, but it doesn't tell us that
you'll be what the punishment will be. Again, all the condition means,
all the only reason you don't have to say the flip side
is it means you won't get what was said in the first
clause. It doesn't tell you you'll get the opposite of that. Okay,
so אלא קא משמע לן, ela ka mashma lan, וחנקי, vechinaki, that
if you did commit adultery, actually it'll be you'll get this terrible
punishment. Okay. בשלמא לרבי מאיר היינו דכתיב, Bishlama leRabbi Meir hainu dechesiv,
according to Rabbi Meir that's what's meant by the פסוק, posuk, הוא
יתחטא בו ביום השלישי וביום השביעי, hu yischata bo bayom hashlishi uvayom
hashvi'i, he will be, you know, purified with the ashes of the
פרה אדומה parah adumah on day three and day seven,
הוא יתחטא בו ביום השלישי וביום השביעי יטהר, hu yischata bo bayom
hashlishi uvayom hashvi'i yitar, and then on day seven he'll be cleansed,
he'll be purified. ואם לא יתחטא ביום השלישי וביום השביעי לא יטהר,
ve'im lo yischata bayom hashlishi uvayom hashvi'i lo yitar, but if he
doesn't do it on day three and day seven, he won't be
cleansed. You have to say the flip side. Okay. So, you know,
it's not implicit. Just 'cause you say 'if you do this it'll
be effective' doesn't necessarily mean 'if you don't do this it won't
be effective'. Do you imagine going through your life like רבי מאיר?
Rabbi Meir? Every time somebody says 'if this', like, 'you didn't say
if not that'. Okay. What, right, exactly, exactly. You know, you know,
'if you do this and hand in the assignment on time you'll
get a full grade'. 'Well, you didn't tell me if I hand
it in late I wouldn't get a full grade!' Okay. Anyway, so
okay, so if you do this then you'll, then
you'll be cleansed, you know, so and but if you don't, then
it won't purify you. So you had to say both. אלא רבי
חנינא בן גמליאל למה לי? Ela Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel lama li?
Why do you have to say both? Obviously if you don't do
what was said, it won't work. איצטריך, Itstrich, you need it. סלקא
דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach amina, I would have thought מצות הזאה בשלישי
ובשביעי, mitzvas hazah beshlishi uvishvi'i, yes, it's telling you that you're supposed,
the מצוה mitzvah is you do it on day three and day
seven, והיכא דעבד בחד מינייהו עבד, veheicha de'avad bechad mineihu avad,
maybe it's like a לכתחילה lechatchila and בדיעבד. bedi'eved. לכתחילה Lechatchila you
should do it day three and day seven, but I might have
thought maybe בדיעבד bedi'eved if you did it only on one of
those it worked. Okay, so they say no, if you didn't do
it both on three and on seven then it won't work. קא
משמע לן, Ka mashma lan, that if you didn't do both it
will not work. Okay, now that we're done with that, we're just
going to explain the פסוקים psukim for a minute. ויזה הטהור על
הטמא ביום השלישי וביום השביעי למה לי? Viyazah hatahor al hatamei bayom
hashlishi uvayom hashvi'i lama li? Why does it have to, after it
sort of said that you need to do day three and seven,
why does it repeat and say it should be sprinkled on day
three and day seven? איצטריך, Itstrich, I need it. סלקא דעתך אמינא
Salka daitach amina שלישי למעוטי שני, shlishi lemutei sheini, שביעי למעוטי שישי,
shvi'i lemutei shishi, דקמבציר ביומי טהרה, dekamivtzir beyomei taharah, I might have
thought that you can't do anything like shorter period than three and
three and and seven. You can't start on day two. Or if
you go to day three then afterwards day six wouldn't be good.
That would that's what I would have thought three and seven are
limiting. But
אבל היכא דעבד בשלישי ובשמיני, aval heicha de'avad beshlishi uvishmini, let's say
you did it on day three and day eight, so actually you're
just extending the process of purification, okay, you're not shortening it you're
extending it, דקמפיש ביומי טהרה, dekamapish beyomei taharah, אימא שפיר דמי, eima
shapir dami, maybe that would be good. So it has to repeat
three and seven to say there can be no variations from three
and seven. Not less, not more, only three and seven. קא משמע
לן. Ka mashma lan. וחטאו ביום השביעי למה לי? Vichito bayom hashvi'i
lama li? Then another פסוק posuk that's extra, why does it have
to and he shall cleanse him on day seven? איצטריך. Itstrich. סלקא
דעתך אמינא Salka daitach amina הני מילי לקדשים, hani mili lekodashim, maybe
you only need this degree of purification to be able to eat
קדשים, kodashim, okay, אבל aval or למקדש lemikdash
as some have the גרסה, girsa, אבל לתרומה aval litrumah בחד נמי
סגי, bechad nami sagi, by תרומה trumah maybe only three or only
seven would be good. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan not. That
anyway, that ends discussion dealing with the extra
פסוקים psukim and what it's clarifying is not רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and רבי חנינא בן גמליאל. Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel. Anyway, from this
it's just general explication. This whole discussion is, you know, it makes
it I think clear that the position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is not just a technical question in הלכות תנאים, hilchos tnaim, but
it's a basic question of language, right? 'Cause it goes through a
lot of פסוקים psukim that don't have to do with like a
formal legal act that's made that's stipulated on certain things. It's like
how do we interpret, why, you know, can we infer the opposite
when you say, you know, this is what you need to do
X, can we infer that if you don't do this it won't
work, the opposite is true? Okay. תוספות Tosafot by the way has
a let's look at the תוספות Tosafot בשלמא, bishlama, interesting little תוספות.
Tosafot. He says
around this issue and he says the following. Okay, sorry. הוא יתחטא.
Hu yischata. תימא מאי ענין זה למחלוקת? Teima mai inyan zeh lemachlokes?
אפילו רבי מאיר למה לי? Afilu Rabbi Meir lama li? According to
Rabbi Meir why do you need to say the flip? אלא בבהרבה
מקומות כתיב Ela beharbeh mekomos kesiv ורחץ במים וטהר verachatz bamayim vetaher
ולא הוצרך לומר ואם לא ירחץ לא יטהר. velo hutzrach lomar ve'im
lo yirchatz lo yitar. Right? Many places it says this is what
you do and this is what it achieves. You know, it's not
it's you know, and I think part of תוספות's Tosafot point is
also there that it's not like descriptive, it's not like explained stated
as conditional, like if you do X then Y. And then you
could say, well, maybe even if I don't do it then why.
But here it's sort of stayed more as descriptive. Do this and
it will achieve the following. You know, wash in water and it
will cleanse you. So that's not if then, it's that this is
what this thing does accomplish. Okay, and therefore, obviously if you don't
do that you don't accomplish that result, right? This act accomplishes the
following thing. ויש לומר Veyesh lomar so isn't that why here you
know same be true here? Why did it need to say the
reverse? How is this related? ויש לומר דלא דמי. Veyesh lomar d'lo
dami. דהתם מילתא דפשיטא, d'hatam milta d'pshita, כיון דמצוה הוא keivan d'mitzvah
hu שציווה הקדוש ברוך הוא, she'tziva haKadosh Baruch Hu, אם לא עשה
לא יצא. im lo asa lo yatza. So God says ורחצת במים
verachatzta bamayim you shall, you know, purify yourself in water. So because
it's a מצוה mitzvah if you don't do it, you don't get
the result. אבל הכא משמע קצת Aval hacha mashma ktzat שבלשון תנאי
she'bilshon tnai a little bit it sounds like you're not describing this
is the effect of the act, but a little bit it describes
like you're saying a condition. מכדי כתיב Michdi ktiv הוא יתחטא hu
yitchata he shall cleanse himself. דהוי כאילו כתיב D'havei k'ilu ktiv אם
יתחטא im yitchata if you cleanse yourself, בו יטהר bo yit'har ולא
כתיב יתחטא ויטהר v'lo ktiv yitchata v'yit'har you shall cleanse yourself, דאז
הוי מצווה v'az havei mitzaveh then it would be a command. So
what תוספות Tosafot is doing is he's sort of dividing the world
into like, I mean I'm going to sort of say three categories.
There's the classic thing that's expressed as a תנאי tnai if X
then Y, if you do this then this will happen. And that's
where רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, well, maybe it'll happen even if
I don't do that, right? Then there's a next case where you're
it's descriptive. This will achieve the following. You shall, you know, go
to the מקוה mikvah and you'll become טהור. tahor. And then there's
the third case where it's a command. You must go to the
מקוה mikvah and you will become טהור. tahor. So תוספות Tosafot says
the case of where it's a מצוה mitzvah it's clear that this
is the, you have to do this to achieve the end result.
But the middle case where it's more descriptive, you will do this
and it will, do we read that as this is achieves this
result and without it the result is not achieved, or do we
read it as
like a condition and therefore maybe you can have the
thing even if the condition isn't met? So that he sort of
sees as a middle case. But I think anyway it's interesting to
see the difference between saying if X then Y and saying this
will achieve the following, right, which is not at all the condition
where you could imagine that without doing it you'll you'll have achieved
that. It says no, this act accomplishes the following thing. Alright, so
that's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי חנינא בן גמליאל, Rabbi Chanina
ben Gamliel, בתנאי בני גד ובני ראובן, bi'tnai bnei Gad u'bnei Reuven,
the גמרא Gemara only discusses the issue about תנאי כפול, tnai kaful,
but as I mentioned the other day there's other things as well
תנאי קודם למעשה, tnai kodem l'ma'aseh, הן קודם ללאו, hen kodem l'lav,
other types of things. Not clear how we פסקן pasken about any
of this. Not clear for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is limited to
a world of תנאים tna'im or applies as a general position about
language.
Okay, very nice rich stuff. Now we move on to the going
back to conditions but more questions about error and deception. Okay, so
let's take a look. המקדש את האשה ואמר, Hamekadesh et ha'isha v'amar,
a man marries a woman and says, you know what, כסבור הייתי
שהיא כהנת kasavur hayiti she'hi kohenet I assumed that she was a
daughter of a כהן, kohen, והרי היא לויה v'harei hi leviya turns
out she's not, she's a בת לויה. bat leviya. לויה והרי היא
כהנת Leviya v'harei hi kohenet I thought she was a לויה leviya
and she turns out she's a כהנת. kohenet. By the way, interesting,
I so funny the way I said it, I said daughter of
a כהן. kohen. But as are often that is the way it's
expressed in the rabbinic literature בת כהן, bat kohen, right, but it
is interesting sometimes it actually directly describes her כהנת, kohenet, לויה, leviya,
and in you know interesting about what status sort of that affords.
Anyway, I thought she was a כהנת, kohenet, turns out she's a
לויה. leviya. I thought she was a לויה, leviya, I only want
a לויה, leviya, now I have a כהנת kohenet and now I
have to worry about that whole family or whatever it is, you
know, which also proves that not
necessarily clear one is better than the other.
Some people might prefer one, some the other. Okay, or עניה והרי
היא עשירה aniya v'harei hi ashira I thought she was poor and
she wasn't used to a high standard of living, now it turns
out she's rich, I can't afford to, you know, or you know
to keep her in the style she's accustomed to. Or עשירה והרי
היא עניה ashira v'harei hi aniya I thought she was rich and
I was going to, you know, get a job with my father-in-law,
והרי היא עניה v'harei hi aniya turns out she's poor. Nevertheless הרי
זו מקודשת. harei zu mekudeshet. None of that matters, okay, she's married.
Why? מפני שלא הטעתו. mipnei shelo hit'atu. She did not deceive him.
As רש"י Rashi says, he deceived himself. Nobody said otherwise. Nobody said
on the condition that. It was, he had thought it, it was
in his mind. And therefore דברים שבלב אינם דברים. devarim she'baleiv einam
devarim. Something that's not articulated cannot make the marriage condition the act
cannot be conditional based on it. Now the problem is that there's
a big gap between saying she didn't deceive him and saying he
didn't say it. Let us say for example, right, that she didn't
deceive him but, you know, people were telling him, oh, do you
know that she's a כהנת kohenet or whatever, and you know and
he said and it's very clear that that's what he was told
and that's the impression he was under, right, and when he was
working with the שדכן shadchan he said, oh what, she's a כהנת,
kohenet, great, I've been looking for a כהנת. kohenet. And the שדכן
shadchan sets them up and the שדכן shadchan had wrong information, but
it was very clear that that was part of his you know
דעת da'at and implication, right, you know and assumption, and he went
ahead. to make the claim because it was not at all obvious
that that was part of his דעת. daas. Could there be cases
where it is part of his דעת, daas, but there's not an
element of deception, right? So it's very unclear about that. Yes. Or
what if she did deceive him, right, but he didn't say like,
"I'm marrying you on the condition that you're a כהנת." kohenes. Would
it still—Right, and what about, right, and how much central would the
deception be? Like, you know, like, well he didn't say the condition
anyway, but let's say she deceived him about something that the court
would decide was trivial. "Oh, well she told me that she had
a, you know, a red Jaguar and it turns out it was
a blue Jaguar," right? So she deceived me, right? So, you know,
right, is it only because these types of things are things that
normally would be a reasonable thing for somebody to care about had
they articulated that? Right? Or let's say she deceived him but—and but
she has an even better case—let's say she deceived him but he
didn't make it as a תנאי. tnai. Right? So let's say she
said—oh I thought you said—oh, so let's say she said, "I am
a—" "Are you a כהנת?" kohenes? "Yes, I'm a כהנת." kohenes. "Okay,
great." And that was said a month ago when the dating process
began, right? Now it's a month later so they're getting married, or
a year later, right? And it hasn't been brought up since, or
whatever, you know. Or let's even say it was brought up since,
you know. So, but it wasn't like made—said explicitly at the time
of the קידושין kiddushin as a תנאי. tnai. Right? So those are
like, yeah, there's a lot of stuff that's not clear here, right,
about how much is it about deception, how much is it about,
you know, implicit דעת, daas, how much is it about something, you
know, that's said explicit, not said explicit. A lot of that that
is left like unexplored. And obviously this is all very relevant. Look,
to some degree deception you could say is a basis for voiding
the קידושין kiddushin even on something relatively—we could speculate, I'm saying because
the משנה mishnah and the discussion in the גמרא gemara is not
clear about this. But we could speculate, right, that deception is a
basis for voiding the קידושין kiddushin even on something relatively trivial because
deception on either side, right, obviously, you know, is a problem in
a marriage if it starts on the basis of deception and so
on. So does deception add weight? We could also speculate that there
are things that are clear to everybody are not דברים שבלב devarim
she-b'lev even if they're not formally articulated as a תנאי, tnai, but
are clear by context and are clear by circumstance that he was
marrying her or she was marrying him on certain assumptions, right? So
we could, you know, so there are cases—but but again, none of
that is actually clear how that would, you know, how that type
of stuff, you know, would play out. And obviously as I mentioned
I think in the past that this is very relevant for issues
of עגונה, agunah, because a case where it turns out that there's
actually if not—if not active deception, but deception by commission, the guy
isn't saying certain things, sometimes there's active deception. He claims that he's
working in some firm and he's actually unemployed, right? I mean it
happens, right? You know, but also there's times where things are not
shared that need to be shared, right? So he doesn't actually mention
that he actually finds himself attracted to other men, you know. I
mean that's—you know, I'm saying so there are issues like that, you
know, and other types of cases where that he actually it turns
out that he's had a history of abuse of abuse, you know.
So all these types of things where you could assume in certain
cases she wouldn't have wanted to marry him had she known that,
right? But is he—where he still could have—would have wanted? Well here
anyway it's her issue, it's his issue with him—his issue with her.
But I'm just saying—but it could obviously be the reverse. Anyway, the
point here is is that there are the issue that, you know,
what needs to be explicit and not explicit, how much does it
have to be deception, how much does it have to be a
presumption of דעת daas that people would obviously not want to get
married had they known those things, right? Those key issues are not—sadly
are not being fully explored. Let's continue in the משנה. mishnah. האומר
לאשה הרי את מקודשת לי לאחר שאתגייר או לאחר שתתגיירי—you're Ha-omer l'ishah
hare at mekudeshes li l'achar she-esgayer o l'achar she-tisgyeri married to me
and it'll take effect after I convert, I'm not Jewish right now.
Or after you convert. Okay. לאחר שאשתחרר—after L'achar she-eshtachrer I'm freed, I'm
a slave right now. או לאחר שתשתחררי—or O l'achar she-tishtachreri you're freed,
you're a slave right now. לאחר שימות בעליך—or L'achar she-yamus ba'aleich you
have this, you know, troublesome little problem that you're currently married, but
after your husband dies, you're married to me. או לאחר שתמות אחותך—or
O l'achar she-tamus achoseich your sister dies because I was married to
your sister and now I can't marry you. לאחר שיחלוץ ליך יבמיך—you
L'achar she-yachalotz lach yevamaich better hope that the husband or the sister
do not die under suspicious circumstances. לאחר שיחלוץ ליך יבמיך—after L'achar she-yachalotz
lach yevamaich your brother-in-law does חליצה chalitzah to you. Okay. In all
those cases, and this would presume that an active קידושין kiddushin when
she requires חליצה chalitzah would not take effect because otherwise who would
care, it could take effect anyway. אינה מקודשת. Einah mekudeshes. None of
that works because that's basically sort of being, you know, as as
we're going to see and this is what the—the גמרא's gemara going
to ignore what I think is so critical the first half of
the משנה. mishnah. and focus on this part. This is דבר שלא
בא לעולם, davar shelo ba le'olam, marrying a woman before either she
or the man are in a position to do קידושין, kiddushin, so
it's not like the physical object isn't בעולם, ba'olam, but the object
and the state object whatever, the person in the state that they
need to be are not yet the right parties of that transaction.
So it's like trying to purchase something that's לא בא לעולם. lo
ba le'olam. Okay, now וכן אומר לחברו אם ילדה אשתך נקבה, vechein
omer lachaveiro im yaleda ishtecha nekeiva, if your wife gives birth to
a daughter, הרי זו מקודשת לי, harei zu mekudeshet li, she's married
to me, and the father marries off his daughter when she's in
utero, okay, אינה מקודשת, eina mekudeshet, she's not married because that's a
real דבר שלא בא לעולם, davar shelo ba le'olam, although it might
depend if the woman is pregnant which is the line here but
that's taken out because that clearly is the discussion in the גמרא
Gemara that gets whatever you know read back into the משנה. mishna.
Okay, so this is basically דבר שלא בא לעולם davar shelo ba
le'olam which is what the גמרא'ס Gemara's gonna focus on. Now by
the way there's an interesting רש"י Rashi on this because רש"י Rashi
says, no, רש"י Rashi coming up. So let's start the גמרא. Gemara.
The גמרא Gemara says like this: תנן התם, tnan hatam, we taught
over there, אין תורמין מן התלוש על המחובר, ein tormin min hatulush
al hamachubar, you can't take תרומה terumah from stuff that's been cut
down from the ground from stuff that's still growing, connected to the
ground. Okay? ואם תרם אין תרומתו תרומה, ve'im taram ein terumato terumah,
bediavad it doesn't work. תרומה terumah only works once wheat has been
harvested. Okay? Now בעי מיניה רב אסי מרבי יוחנן, bei minei Rav
Assi meRabbi Yochanan, Rav Assi asked Rabbi Yochanan, אמר פירות ערוגה זו
תלושין יהיו תרומה על פירות ערוגה זו מחוברים, amar peirot aruga zu
telushin yihiyu terumah al peirot aruga zu mechubarin, let's say you're מפריש
תרומה mafrish terumah and you say the fruit of this orchard will
be of this you know patch which the fruit's been harvested will
be תרומה terumah on the fruit of that patch that has yet
to be harvested. And when will לכשינתלשו, lichsheyitlashu, once they get harvested.
ונתלשו מהו, venitlashu mahu, will that work? That's sort of doing it
it'll take effect in the future when the thing is in a
state where it can take effect, very similar to our משנה. mishna.
Okay? Now here's the strange רש"י Rashi because לכשינתלשו lichsheyitlashu makes it
sound very clear that you're saying it'll take effect then. How can
it take effect now? Right? So the question is can I do
an act now on an object that's not yet
in the right state
that'll take effect when it gets into the right state? That seems
very clear but there's a bizarre רש"י. Rashi. If you look at
רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, ונתלשו מהו, venitlashu mahu, four lines from
the bottom, שתהא תרומה למפרע. shetehei terumah lemafrea. Okay, מידי דהוי אדבר
שלא בא לעולם, midi dehavei adavar shelo ba le'olam, retroactively. So that's
very bizarre and it doesn't fit with the rest of the סוגיא,
sugya, right? It's hard enough to think that it could happen once
they get harvested, but to think that retroactively when they get harvested
it'll take effect now if they're still attached, right, that's obviously a
question of a different nature. Anyway but that was his question: can
I do the act now to take effect when the thing gets
to the right state? אמר ליה כל שבידו לאו כמחוסר מעשה דמי,
amar leih kol shebeyado lav kimechusar ma'aseh dami, if it's in your
hand to do it, all you have to do is go and
pluck them, they're your fruits, okay, then it's not like it's not
yet in the right state. Then it's considered like it's already in
the right state or close enough and it takes effect. Now maybe
that's why רש"י Rashi thinks it works retroactively, because since I could
do it and it's so ready to be done and I have
the ability to do it it's like they're already picked. Okay? But
that's sort of like a different principle. That's like כל העומד לקצוץ
כקצוץ דמי, kol ha'omeid liktzotz kiktzotz dami, if it's getting ready to
be harvested it's like, but I don't think that that's what the
גמרא Gemara is saying. The גמרא Gemara is saying is it's not
considered שלא בא לעולם shelo ba le'olam because you have enough weight
to make it happen that it's not considered so much out of
your control that therefore you have enough control over the reality that
therefore you can say that it will take effect later. The same
way if the woman is single and I'm single or whatever and
I can say to the woman you're married to me אחר שלושים
יום, achar sheloshim yom, I can say it'll happen at that time
if I can bring about that time. Even though you yourself thirty
days from now haven't yet been בא לעולם ba le'olam so to
speak. Right, exactly. It's not a problem of separating the act and
the effect. The problem is is when the necessary components of the
act aren't present now. But if you have the ability of making
that happen then that's not a problem and it can take effect
later I would say, not now but later. By the way, just
here's an interesting thing which is very relevant for this. The רמב"ם
Rambam says, I think it's רמב"ם Rambam המגיד משנה Maggid Mishneh or
whatever, that let's say I say to you Jacob, I'm going to
sell you you know whatever you know I'm going to sell you
lumber you know at this price and I have a supplier okay
that actually provides me the lumber and he's got tons of lumber
available and there's a hundred suppliers available, can I do the sale
to you before I've purchased the lumber? Okay? It's לא בא לעולם,
lo ba le'olam, I don't have it yet, it's not mine. But
is the fact that it's readily available in the open market and
I can just go and do it that's a type of a
בידו beyado mean that I'm able to sell it to you? So
there's a רמב"ם Rambam that says basically yes and that's also very
relevant in the... how could you sell something you don't have? Well,
because obviously you can have it and it's trivial to have it
if you're willing to pay the money for it, right? So anyway,
so that's like a כל שבידו. kol shebeyado. So it's enough that
it is there that you can actually do it, but again, it
seems from the גמרא Gemara that it will take effect later, not
now, לכשישתחרר. lechisheishtachrer. So he says כל שבידו, kol shebeyado, where are
we? כל שבידו לאו כמחוסר מעשה דמי. kol shebeyado lav kemehussar maaseh
dami. I'll ask you on this. האומר לאשה הרי את מקודשת לי
לאחר שאתגייר, haomer leishah harei at mekudeshet li leachar sheitgayyer, you're married
to me after I convert, לאחר שתתגיירי, leachar shetitgayyeri, you convert, לאחר
שאשתחרר leachar sheeshtachrer או לאחר שתשתחררי, o leachar shetishtachreri, I'm freed, you're
freed, לאחר שימות בעליך, leachar sheyamut baaleich, your husband dies, לאחר שתמות
אחותיך, leachar shetamut achoteich, your sister dies, לאחר שיחלוץ ליך יבמיך, leachar
sheyachalotz lich yevameich, or your brother-in-law does חליצה, chalitzah, אינה מקודשת. eina
mekudeshet. Now בשלמא כולהו, bishlama kullahun, all of those cases, לאו בידו,
lav beyado, he couldn't control. אלא גר, ela ger, but converting, הוה
בידו, hava beyado, he can convert, that's in his hand! Yeah, it's
a good thing he never had to deal with Israeli rabbinate. So
the גמרא Gemara says גר נמי לאו בידו. ger nami lav beyado.
No, in the גמרא, Gemara, that's also not בידו. beyado. דאמר רבי
חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן גר שצריך שלשה, deamar Rabbi Chiyya
bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan ger shetzarich shlosha, a גר ger needs
a בית דין beit din of three. מאי טעמא? mai taama? משפט
כתיב ביה. mishpat ktiv bei. It's like it says משפט. mishpat. משפט
אחד יהיה לכם כגר כאזרח הארץ. mishpat echad yihyeh lachem kager kaezrach
haaretz. So it's like any judgment, judgment requires a בית דין. beit
din. כדין, kedin, it's like it's like a normal court case. And
therefore, since it needs three, מי יימר דמזדקקו להו הני תלתא? mi
yeimar demizdakaku leh hani tlata? Who says that you're going to be
able to convene a בית דין? beit din? That they'll be... Now,
of course, the גמרא Gemara doesn't make it sound like like who
says that they will not they will approve of your level of
שמירת מצוות shmirat mitzvot or that they're going to run you through
the ringer or whatever, the גמרא Gemara makes it just sound like,
yeah, who can promise that you'll be able to get a בית
דין beit din together? You know, it's not totally your decision, you're
dependent on other people to convene a בית דין, beit din, etc.
Okay, but again, it's pretty sad and ironic when you see when
you realize like the realities nowadays, nobody would have ever had a
הוה אמינא hava mina that גר ger was בידו. beyado. Anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. מסקיף לה ר' אבא בר
ממל. maskif lah Rabbi Abba bar Memel. Now we're going to continue
to challenge this idea that בידו beyado is not a problem. אלא
מעתה הנותן פרוטה לשפחתו, ela meata hanoten prutah lshifchato, somebody gives a
master gives a פרוטה prutah to his slave, his female slave that
he can free, and if he frees her she becomes Jewish, ואמר
לה הרי את מקודשת לי לאחר שאשחרריך, veamar lah harei at mekudeshet
li leachar sheashachreirich, you are married to me after I free you.
That's בידו. beyado. הכי נמי דהוי קידושין, hachi nami dehavi kidushin, will
that work? So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, הכי השתא? hachi
hashta? How could you compare them? Just a little what's a trigger
warning for the next line in the גמרא. Gemara. הכי השתא התם
מעיקרא בהמה השתא דעת אחרת. hachi hashta hatam meikara behemah hashta daat
acheret. So there she was an animal, she wasn't really... it wasn't
like you really can marry anybody yet, she was still a slave,
okay, and then she becomes a human being, somebody with agency. So
obviously even if it was בידו, beyado, it's completely like a יש
מאין, yesh meayin, it's like the thing didn't exist בכלל. bichlal. Okay,
so now obviously that is deeply disturbing about describing that the idea
of a slave as בהמה, behemah, especially you wonder how the גמרא
Gemara could say that given that that slaves are obligated in מצוות,
mitzvot, you know. So, you know, it's so dehumanizing. So what I
would like to... not so... I mean, it is dehumanizing. What I
would like to say, and you could decide whether this is apologetics
or not, but I would like to say is that the גמרא
Gemara is just doing this as a way of expressing that it's
a like a complete... like the whole identity has shifted. It's not
just a... you know, like the Greeks used to define a difference
between what's called essential and accidental attributes. Like the fact that this
table is brown is an accidental attribute. The fact that it has
a surface or four legs, that's like an essential attribute. Without that,
it wouldn't be a table, right? So to what degree do you
say that the thing is like... בכלל... bichlal... בידו beyado means it's
basically here but it's not fully in the state it needs to
be for the act, but I can change that state and make
it fit for that act, and therefore it's like we can do
the act right now. Okay, but let's say it's a complete transformation,
which similarly, by the way, the גמרא Gemara could have said by
the גר ger case, right? Like this always bothered me because רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir is of the position that you can be... you
can do דבר שלא בא לעולם. davar shelo ba laolam. According to
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, if somebody says you're married to me after
you convert or after I convert, he says that works. And I
never understood that. How can you begin to do a halakhic transaction
if one of the parties is not Jewish? Right? It's not like
you have the basic essentials but there's a little bit of a
problem, you don't own the object yet or the fruit haven't been
produced yet but they're going to naturally... like you fundamentally, how do
you start a halakhic transaction if one of the parties isn't Jewish?
You know? So that's how I would like to read what this
גמרא Gemara is saying is that בידו beyado is not enough if
the object is seen as or the other, you know, one of
the essentials is seen as so completely not present and it would
be a complete transformation, you know, or you know type of a
thing, you know, in terms of that person. So that's anyway how
I would like to read that. I'm getting no response. I'm getting
the sense everybody wants to just move on after this line. Okay.
Stop belaboring the point. Let's go on. Okay, moving on. But I
do think it's an important legal point. Okay, now. So let's take
a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this. Yes, I mean, just
to think in that one point, if since theory that this person
has become to go through this transformation, right, it's like perhaps the
status is not necessarily talking about some aspect of this person. I
mean, you're talking about one aspect, but another aspect, I don't know
if it's like belittling them or belittling the status. Right, I understand.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. ולהא דאמר רבי אושעיא,
V'leha d'amar Rabbi Oshaya, that's what רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya said. הנותן
שתי פרוטות לאשתו ואמר לה הרי את מקודשת לי לאחר שאגרשך, Hanoten
shtei prutot l'ishto v'amar lah harei at mekudeshet li l'achar she'agareshach, you're
married to me after I divorce you. Okay, so romantic. Okay, and
he can divorce her and it's unilateral, אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshet. So
the גמרא Gemara says, הכי נמי לרבי יוחנן תהוי קידושין, hachi nami
l'Rabbi Yochanan tehvei kiddushin, would it work for רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan?
Because since he can divorce her, so it's בידו, biyado, so he
can create that state, so let it work and let her be
married after he divorces her. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אי
דבידו לגרשה, i d'biyado l'garshah, yes, he can unilaterally divorce her, בידו
לקדשה? biyado l'kadshah? Can he unilaterally marry her? He can't. Now, of
course that's funny because she's agreeing, she accepts the ring. So the
only scene the way of this second marriage is the divorce which
is completely under his control. Okay, yes, I don't know how that
ever applies, I mean, where there are two sides, whatever. Right, oh
you mean like what the גמרא Gemara said before about the case
of the גר. ger. All of those cases you could say, like,
you know, yes, that if it's that בידו biyado doesn't work if
it's a two-sided, if what you're trying to effect is a two-sided
transaction. Right, and it's strange, why should that matter if the other
side is agreeing right now? Yes, I really don't understand why that
matters so much. Okay, and then you're right that obviously all your
קידושין kiddushin questions would immediately be answered. It's only going to be
an issue in something like תרומה terumah or a גט get which
is a complete one-sided transaction. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says fine.
תיפשוט דבעיא רבי אושעיא, tipshot d'ba'aya Rabbi Oshaya, so now that you
said that this doesn't work because the other side is not בידו,
biyado, so תיפשוט דבעיא רבי אושעיא, tipshot d'ba'aya Rabbi Oshaya, let's use
this to come to a conclusion of the question that was raised
by רבי אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya. What did רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya ask?
הנותן שתי פרוטות לאשה, Hanoten shtei prutot l'ishah, a man gave two
פרוטות prutot to a woman, two rings. Okay. באחת אמר לה התקדשי
לי היום, B'achat amar lah hitkadshi li hayom, one he said, marry
me today. ובאחת אמר לה התקדשי לי לאחר שאגרשך, U'v'achat amar lah
hitkadshi li l'achar she'agareshach, but I've got some plans, okay, so I'm
going to divorce you, but then it'll be you'll be remarried to
me after I divorce you. I cannot figure out what logic might
be behind this, but okay. Anyway, תיפשוט מינה דלא הוי קידושין, tipshot
minah d'lo havei kiddushin, let's say it won't work because you've just
said that it's considered to be not בידו biyado because there's another
side. So here too there's another side, it should be just like
the case of him trying to marry her once they're already married.
So the גמרא Gemara says, you know, after they get after they
get divorced, no, דילמא, dilma, no, no, you can make a distinction.
דילמא כי היכי דתפסי קידושין השתא תפסי נמי לאחר כן. Dilma ki
heichi d'tafsi kiddushin hashta tafsi nami l'achar ken. No, no. Here it's
different. Here she's not yet married to him. So since the first,
she's in a state where he can do an act of קידושין
kiddushin to her. So he just want, right, because she's single right
now. So he wants to do two acts: this act to take
effect now, and the other act, which I could say takes effect
now, I'm going to say is going to take effect later after
you get divorced from me. Okay. To the same woman. Yeah, yeah,
yeah. Same woman, same woman. So he says marry me with this
ring now and with this ring after I divorce, should be חל,
chal, the קידושין kiddushin should be חל chal for after I divorce
you because I'm planning on divorcing you. Okay, exactly. But no, she
took the ring. So there it says, here you've got the right
components for an act of קידושין. kiddushin. You got a man, you
got a single woman, she's agreeing to take the כסף. kesef. You
could do an act of קידושין, kiddushin, it could be effective right
now. So then you can postpone the effect for a later time
even though what's going to intervene will be a marriage and a
divorce. But nevertheless, it's possible to do a קידושין kiddushin right now.
In the other case, the man says to his wife the woman
who's married to him, I am marrying you. Now, you cannot marry
a woman who's already married, even to you. Okay. You can do
a what are the ceremonies they do, a reaffirmation of vows, but
you cannot do another קידושין kiddushin while she's married to him. So
the act of קידושין kiddushin is not meaningful. We want to make
it meaningful by saying it's בידו לגרשה. biyado l'garshah. But that's not
enough to make it seen as meaningful if it's something that also
requires her to agree. And so that was sort of that weird
combination. But that's when it starts off in a state which the
act of קידושין kiddushin cannot be happening. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara
goes on. תני כוותיה דרבי יוחנן, Tani kavateih d'Rabbi Yochanan, we talk
like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that the idea of בידו biyado makes
it possible to do. even though the components are not fully here.
אין תורמין מן התלוש על המחובר. Ein tormin min hatalush al hamachubur.
You cannot take from harvested on growing produce. ואם תרם תרומתו תרומה,
V'im taram terumaso terumah, if you do it doesn't work. כיצד, Keisad,
what would... how would that play out? אמר פירות ערוגה זו תלושין
יהיו תרומה על פירות ערוגה זו מחוברת, Amar peiros arugah zo tlushin
yihyu terumah al peiros arugah zo mechuberes, these harvested fruits will be
תרומה terumah on these fruits that are still growing. פירות ערוגה זו
מחוברת יהיו תרומה על פירות ערוגה זו תלושין, Peiros arugah zo mechuberes
yihyu terumah al peiros arugah zo tlushin, or the reverse, these growing
fruits will be תרומה terumah on these harvested fruits. לא אמר כלום,
Lo amar klum, it does not work. אבל אמר, Aval amar, but
if somebody said, לכשינתלשו, Lichsheyitlashu, they'll take effect once they get harvested,
ונתלשו, venitlashu,
and then they are harvested. דבריו קיימין, Devarav kayamin, it does work.
Very nice. Exactly what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said. That would make
something not considered to be דבר שלא בא לעולם. davar shelo ba
la'olam. That would be like you already have the components here and
it can work. And as I said, very relevant for the whole
issue about buying futures, etc. or selling, you know, selling futures, not
selling futures, whatever. Anyway, יתר על כן אמר רבי אלעזר בן יעקב.
Yesser al ken amar Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov. Yeah, buying futures. יתר
על כן אמר רבי אלעזר בן יעקב, Yesser al ken amar Rabbi
Elazar ben Yaakov,
רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov even went further. אפילו
אמר פירות ערוגה זו תלושין יהיו תרומה על פירות ערוגה זו מחוברת,
Afilu amar peiros arugah zo tlushin yihyu terumah al peiros arugah zo
mechuberes, or פירות ערוגה זו מחוברת יהיו תרומה על פירות ערוגה זו
תלושין, peiros arugah zo mechuberes yihyu terumah al peiros arugah zo tlushin,
לכשיביאו שליש, lichsheyaviu shelish, even if you didn't say once they're harvested,
even if all you said is, once they, they're not even yet
ripe, they're unripe, they're not even a third ripe, and they have
to be a third ripe. If you harvest your grain before it's
a third ripe, you cannot take תרומה terumah on it. תרומה Terumah
can only be taken on ripened grain, and ripened grain is defined
as a third ripe. There's actually ways of seeing, you know, what
that stage, what that stage is. Okay? So this grain is not
only not harvested, which is בידו, beyado, but it's not even yet
ripened, and it's not בידו beyado to ripen it. Okay? And nevertheless,
you say it'll take effect when they ripen, ונתלשו, venitlashu, and it's
harvested. והביאו שליש ונתלשו, Vehevi'u shelish venitlashu, and they ripened and were
harvested. So דבריו קיימין, devarav kayamin, it works. So, oh, so you
see that he's willing to say that even when it's even something
that's not בידו, beyado, you can do a דבר שלא בא לעולם.
davar shelo ba la'olam. Now, is that because that would be a
natural thing? You know, there's degrees of לא בא לעולם. lo ba
la'olam. If everything works as it's supposed to, they'll ripen. The fact
that I say when your husband dies, or your sister dies, that's
a different type of a לא בא לעולם lo ba la'olam than
when the grain ripens. Okay? But nevertheless, he says that that works.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבא לא אמר
רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אלא בשחת. Amar Rava lo amar Rabbi Elazar
ben Yaakov ella beshachas. So that's what we're all going to qualify.
He only said that by grain that already is like standing grain
and ready to be fodder. אבל אגם, Aval agam, if it's very
like, you know, unripe grain, if it's like if it's like at
a vegetable stage, you know, it's, you know, green and so on
and it's not hasn't really, you know, risen, then לא, lo, then
it would not be like the thing even existed at all. So
that's not like how likely it'll be that it'll ripen. But just
sort of the discussion in the גמרא Gemara that everybody's uncomfortable with,
how much is the thing seen as being present at all? Okay?
If it's just little shoots coming from the ground, you can't say
it. If it's already standing grain that's not ripened, then it's more
seen as being present. אמר רב יוסף אפילו באגם. Amar Rav Yosef
afilu ba'agam. No, he would say it even if it's just little
shoots coming from the ground. מאי משמע דהאי אגם לישנא דבוצלנא הוא?
Mai mashma dehai agam lishna debutzalna hu? How do you know אגם
agam means like a type of a leek, like some type of
a thing that's, you know, like that like a little hanging over
type of a green plant? אגם? Agam? אמר רב אלעזר דאמר קרא
הלכוף כאגמון ראשו. Amar Rav Elazar d'amar kra halachof k'agmon rosho. Will
you bend down your head like an אגמון? agmon? It's like a
type of a, you know, like a plant that like leans over.
Okay, so it's like a little young shoot. So that's an interesting
question. When רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov said it,
does it have to really be like present and just, you know,
or does it even if it's almost not even existing, you know,
or barely existing?
Now, כמאן אזלא הא דתניא, Keman azla ha d'tanya, who's it going
like that which is taught in the ברייתא? Baraita? האומר לחבירו אם
ילדה אשתך נקבה מקודשת לי, Haomer lachaveiro im yalda ishtecha nekeivah mekudeshes
li, if somebody said your, you know, if your wife gives birth
to a daughter she'll be married, לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum,
it's not good. ואמר רבי חנינא לא שנו אלא שאין אשתו מעוברת,
V'amar Rabbi Chanina lo shanu ella she'ein ishto me'uberes, that only if
she's not pregnant. אבל אשתו מעוברת, Aval ishto me'uberes, if she's pregnant,
דבריו קיימין, devarav kayamin, it works. So who's that going like? So
that's a type of a thing where like naturally she would give
birth, the thing is present, you know. So כמאן? keman? אי כרבא
כשהוכר עוברה, Ei k'Rava keshehurkar ubrah, either it's like, now this רש"י
Rashi says, is following רבי אלעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov.
Following רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov that says that
when you say when the grain ripens it works, that if things
continue on their natural and expected course it will come about naturally
even though it's not בידו, beyado, and that's enough to consider the
thing present. Right? Everybody get it? There's one stage of בידו, beyado,
you can make it happen. There's another stage you can't make it
happen, but naturally it should happen. Right? There's another thing where there's
a lot of obstacles. So here רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar
ben Yaakov is saying if it naturally should happen, you can go
ahead with the transaction or קידושין Kiddushin or whatever. So therefore the
woman is pregnant, it'll naturally happen, so according to... her, but does
she, the pregnancy, does it have to be visible? So that's the
debate about whether the grain has to be standing and seen as
really present, or whether even if it's a young shoot, and it's
not really even the same thing, would that, would it even work
in that case? So איכא דאמרי Ika d'Amri כשהוכר עוברה keshehukar ubra
for רבה Rabba that would work according to רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
Rebbi Eliezer Ben Yaakov when the, the pregnancy, when the fetus is
visible, is noticeable, not visible, noticeable, because then it's like the standing
grain. ולרב יוסף u'leRav Yosef אף על פי שלא הוכר עוברה, af
al pi shelo hukar ubra, but for רב יוסף Rav Yosef even
without that, because according to him even if it's almost like the
thing isn't even, doesn't seriously exist, it still nevertheless works if it'll
come about in a natural way. Okay, and let's just read the
final version of this one minute. ואיכא דאמרי v'ika d'amri אמר רבה
amar Rabba לא אמר רבי אליעזר בן יעקב lo amar Rebbi Eliezer
Ben Yaakov אלא בשחת דבי כרשא. ela b'shachat d'bei kirsha. רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב Rebbi Eliezer Ben Yaakov only said it by a standing
grain that is from a, a field that is, that is, that
gets what it needs from rainwater. אבל בשחת דבי שקיא, aval b'shachat
d'bei shakya, but from grain that needs to be irrigated, לא, lo,
because then maybe is a
little bit more tentative, it won't, you know, you're not as confident,
it's not as clear that it'll, the end result will come about.
Okay. רב יוסף אמר Rav Yosef amar אפילו בשחת דבי שקיא. afilu
b'shachat d'bei shakya. No, no, no, even if it is an irrigated
field, it still, you know, naturally should happen. Okay, but they both
say it has to be standing grain, it can't be like young
shoots. So now that they both at least agree, there's a question
about how, you know, tentative, how, how confident you are that it'll
naturally happen, but they both agree according to him that it has
to be like visible, it has to be like significant, like present
in a significant way. So according to that, כמאן אזלא הא דתניא
k'man azla ha d'tanya האומר לחברו ha'omer l'chavero אם ילדה אשתך נקבה
מקודשת לי im yalda ishtecha nekeva mekudeshet li לא אמר כלום. lo
amar klum. ואמר רבי חנינא ve'amar Rabbi Chanina לא שנו אלא שאין
אשתו מעוברת lo shanu ela she'ein ishto me'uberet אבל אשתו מעוברת ודאי
קיימין aval ishto me'uberet vadai kayamin that it would work if the
woman was, was pregnant. So כמאן, k'man, who's that going like? כשהוכר
עוברה ודברי הכל. keshehukar ubra vedivrei hakol. Here, the way we're saying
it now, everybody would agree that the fetus would have to be
noticeable. Okay, because here we're saying that everybody says according to רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב Rebbi Eliezer Ben Yaakov as to who we read,
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rebbi Eliezer Ben Yaakov, that, that it's not
enough if it's a young shoot. It has to be standing grain.
It has to be like the thing is present. Okay, so what
we have now is the following positions. You can never be מקדיש
דבר makdish davar or מקדש mekadesh or מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם.
makneh davar shelo ba l'olam. You can do it if it's בידו
beyado to bring the thing
about, that's רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. You can do it even if
it's not בידו, beyado, but if it'll be a natural expected result,
which is like the case of the grain being, ripening or the
woman giving birth. Okay, and then question about what if there's some,
what if it's not totally confident about that end result, like irrigated
field, non-irrigated field. And then even more extreme position, that if it'll
naturally come about even if the thing is not so visibly present
yet, it will still work. So different degrees of how much is
the thing considered to be present, you know, that we can say
that it can work even though it's לא בא לעולם. lo ba
l'olam. Jacob, you had a question.
Hi, so the תניא, tanya, I missed some of the
פלפול, pilpul, but like it...
I wouldn't have called that פלפול pilpul but okay.
Anyway, some of the analysis.
The analysis, but, but like it seems, like it seems like one,
me, I wonder if one of the underlying discussions going on is
also like how do different people relate to these different acts and
their of certainty or uncertainty. Like how certain is it that a
woman who is pregnant will give birth versus that a fruit that
is on a tree will ripen?
You know, like that experiential, like not just what the, what the
statistics show, but it's...
Or like is this something that feels... Like maybe the מחלוקת machloket
about the, about a woman who's pregnant is more about like how...
How certain do I
feel.
Right, I think that that's a really good point. Right. Like and
that's what I said, like the expected result is whatever, but does
that mean at the experiential level that's what we assume is going
to happen and how much does it relate to the actual facts
of what are the percentages, you know, that it does and doesn't
happen. That is a very good question. Okay, we'll end here. חג
שמח. Chag Sameach.